Strike Files of the U.S. Department of Justice, Pt. 1 on Microfilm 5897 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Strike Files of the U.S. Department of Justice, Pt. 1 on Microfilm
1894- 1941
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Department of Justice
5897 mf
2.22 cubic feet
20 microfilm reels
Microfilm, records.
2638061
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
M. Clark, January 28, 2016
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 10, 2016
Biographical / Historical
The United States Department of Justice (DOJ), also known as the Justice Department, is the U.S. federal executive department responsible for the enforcement of the law and administration of justice, equivalent to the justice or interior ministries of other countries.
The Department is led by the Attorney General, who is nominated by the President and confirmed by the Senate and is a member of the Cabinet. [Wikipedia]
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Strikes and lockouts -- United States -- History -- Sources; Labor unions -- United States -- History -- Sources; Labor laws and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources; United States. Dept. of Justice
2638061
- Casefile 16-1 (Reel 1)
  - Subfile 1. Alabama, 1894-1895; 1 (Reel 1)
    Scope and Contents
    July 6, 1894-May 7,1895. 9pp. Subject: U.S Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property. Begins at 0000.
  - Subfile 8. Arizona Territory, 1894-1897; 2 (Reel 1)
    June 29, 1894-Febuary 10, 1897. 44pp. Subjects: Authorization of dismissal of railroad employees who were members of labor organizations; U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of U.S. troops and deputies guarding railroad property, mob violence and intimidation; federal intervention to protect mail routes and interstate commerce. Begins at 0009
  - Subfile 9. Arkansas, 1894-1895; 3 (Reel 1)
    July 2, 1894-April 26, 1895. 48pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; indictment and trial of local strike leaders for delay of U.S. mail and interference with interstate commerce; mob violence and intimidation. Begins at 0053.
  - Subfile 11. California, 1894-1899; 4 (Reel 1)
    June 28, 1894-October 4, 1899. 339 pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; indictment and trial of members and leadership of the American Railway Union for delay of U.S. mail and interference with interstate commerce; rest of persons for causing trail wreck; cooperation with Illinois Eugene V. Debs, et al.; use of federal troops in labor disturbances; mob violence and intimidation; failure of state militia to control situation due to sympathy with strikers. Begins at 0101.
  - Subfile 13. Colorado, 1894-1896; 5 (Reel 1)
    July 1, 1894-June 18, 1896. 85pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; mob violence and intimidation; sympathy and support for strikers by townspeople. Begins at 0448.
  - Subfile 14. Connecticut, 1894; 6 (Reel 1)
    July 6,1894. 5pp. Subjects: Citizen request for federal intervention against American Railway Union strike. Begins at 0533.
  - Subfile 16. District of Columbia, 1894-1895; 7 (Reel 1)
    June 30, 1894-November 2, 1895. 62pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; requests by Union Pacific Rail Road of payment of transportation expenses and cash advances made by clemency in various U.S. trials of strikers and American Railway Union leadership cases; coordination of nationwide efforts to put down strike and Illinois prosecution of Eugene V. Debs.et al;lrequests of use of federal troops against strikers; mob violence and intimidation in California, Colorado, Idaho, Illinois, and New Mexico. Begins at 033.
  - Subfile 22. Idaho, 1894-1898; 8 (Reel 1)
    June 20, 1894-July 7, 1898. 52pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incused and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; mob violence and intimidation; U.S. Circuit Court order for protection of Northern Pacific Railroad; requests of use of federal troops. Begins at 0600.
  - Subfile 23, Section 1. Illinois, 1894; 9 (Reel 1)
    June 29, 1894-July 18, 1894. 183pp. Subjects: Trial of Eugene V. Debs, et al., leaders of the American Railway Union; use of federal troops; U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; mob violence and intimidation; requests for use of federal troops against strikers in Illinois and California; U.S. Department of Justice decision to strikers in Illinois and California; U.S. Department of Justice decision to intervene for the protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce. Begins at 0652.
- Casefile 16-1. Continued (Reel 2)
  - Subfile 23, Section 2. Illinois, 1894-1895; 1 (Reel 2)
    July 18 1894-January 9, 1895. 179pp. Subjects: Trial of Eugene V. Debs, et al., leaders of the American Railway Union; habeas corpus proceedings; U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; mob violence and intimidation; lists of railroad employees employed as deputies; copies of American Railway Union documents for use in prosecutions. Begins at 0000.
  - Subfile 23, Section 3. Illinois, 1895; 2 (Reel 2)
    January 9-November1, 1895. 207pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; mob violence and intimidation; trial of Eugene V. debs, et al., leaders of the American Railroad Union; habeas corpus proceedings; requests for reimbursement of railroads and the Railroad Managers' Association for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals; labor disturbances in mining regions of Illinois, coordination between prosecutors and defense attorney Clarence Darrow. Begins a 0179.
  - Subfile 23, Section 4. Illinois, 1894-1895; 3 (Reel 2)
    November 9, 1894-Jul 13, 1895. 129pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; mob violence and intimidation; requests for reimbursement of railroads and the Railroad Managers' Association for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals; trial of Eugene V. debs, et al., leaders of the American Railroad Union; use of railroad employees as deputies; mob violence and intimidation. Begins at 0386.
  - Subfile 26, Indiana, 1894-1903; 4 (Reel 2)
    June 30, 1894-July 3, 1903. 66pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; mob violence and intimidation; requests of reimbursement of railroads for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals; use of railroad employees as deputies; mob violence and intimidation, requests for the use of federal troops. Begins at 0515.
  - Subfile 27. Iowa, 1894-1896; 5 (Reel 2)
    July 3, 1894-March 23, 1896. 33pp. Subjects: U.S Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; mob violence and intimidation; dispute over use of federal troops in Illinois; mob violence and intimidation; interference with interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0581.
  - Subfile 29. Kansas, 1894-1895; 6 (Reel 2)
    July 3 1894-July 11,1895. 35pp. Subjects: trial of Eugene V. Debs, et al., leaders of the American Railway Union; U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; interference with interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0614.
  - Subfile 30. Kentucky, 1894-1898; 7 (Reel 2)
    July 7, 1894-October 15, 1898. 29pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; requests for reimbursement of railroads for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals; protection of U.S. mails and interference with interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0649.
  - Subfile 32. Louisiana, 1894-1895; 8 (Reel 2)
    July 5, 1894-March18, 1895. 9pp. Subjects Arrests and trials for inciting a general strike; protection of U.S. mails and interference with interstate commerce as justification of federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0678.
  - Subfile 34. Maine, 1895; 9 (Reel 2)
    September 10, 1895. 3pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal statement that no expenses were incurred. Begins at 0687.
  - Subfile 36. Massachusetts, 1894; 10 (Reel 2)
    July 6-August 23, 1894. 8pp. Subjects: Trial of Eugene V. Debs, et al., leaders of the American Railway Union; public support for and opposition to actions of strikers. Begins at 0690.
  - Subfile 37. Michigan, 1894-1895; 11 (Reel 2)
    Jul 3, 1894-October 14, 1895. 44pp. Arrest and trial of person accused of wrecking train carrying U.S. mails; U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; request for use of federal troops; interference with interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0698.
  - Subfile 39. Minnesota, 1894-1896; 12 (Reel 2)
    July 9, 1894-May 13, 1896. 32pp. Subjects: Requests for reimbursement of railroads for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals; U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; trial of a person accused of being a striker and rioter; protection of U.S. mails and interference with interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0742.
  - Subfile 40. Mississippi, 1894; 13 (Reel 2)
    July 7,1894. 3pp. Subjects: Protection of U.S. mails and interference with interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0774.
- Casefile 16-1. Continued (Reel 3)
  - Subfile 42. Missouri, 1894-1895; 1 (Reel 3)
    July 1, 1894-Octobe 13. 1895. 178pp. Subjects: Injunction against members and local leaders of the American Railway Union for interfering with normal operations of railroads during strike; employment of special counsel in case, U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0000.
  - Subfile 44. Montana, 1894; 2 (Reel 3)
    July 2-October 26, 1894. 23pp. Subject: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property. Begins at 0178.
  - Subfile 45. Nebraska, 1894-1895; 3 (Reel 3)
    July 3, 1894-April 12, 1895. 18pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; request for federal troops and mob violence and intimidation in Wyoming. Begins at 0201.
  - Subfile 46. Nevada, 1894-1896; 4 (Reel 3)
    July 3, 1894-March 16, 1896. 38pp. Subjects: Indictment and trial of members and local leaders of the American Railway Union for obstruction of U.S. mails and interference with interstate commerce; U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; requests for reimbursement of railroads for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals. Begins at 0219.
  - Subfile 47. New Hampshire, 1894; 5 (Reel 3)
    July 5, 1894. 4pp. Subject: Support for the protection of U.S. mails and interference with interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0257.
  - Subfile 49. New Mexico Territory, 1894-1896; 6 (Reel 3)
    June 27, 1894-January 30, 1896. 74pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; requests for reimbursement of railroads for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals; mob violence and intimidation; use of federal troops to restore order; protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0261.
  - Subfile 50. New York, 1894; 7 (Reel 3)
    July 3-August 1, 1894. 22pp. Subjects: reports from railroad officials regarding strike situation in Iowa, Louisiana, Texas, Missouri, Tennessee, Minnesota, Arkansas, and California. Begins at 0335.
  - Subfile 56. North Dakota, 1894-1895; 8 (Reel 3)
    July 16, 1894-November 7, 1895. 39pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike; indictment and trial of persons involved in mob violence and intimidation. Begins at 0357.
  - Subfile 57. Ohio, 1894-1895; 9 (Reel 3)
    July 3, 1894-October 26, 1895. 141pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; requests for reimbursement of railroads for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals; employment of private detectives as deputies; protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike; arrest and trial of Frank W. Phelan of the American Railway Union; use of injunctions in labor disputes. Begins at 0396.
  - Subfile 59, Section A. Oklahoma Territory, 1894-1895; 10 (Reel 3)
    July 13, 1894-July 9, 1896. 22pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; use of injunctions in labor disputes; mob violence and intimidation. Begins at 0537.
  - Subfile 59. Section B. Indian Territory, 1894-1895; 11 (Reel 3)
    July 9, 1894-December 9, 1895. 21pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0559.
  - Subfile 61. Oregon, 1894; 12 (Reel 3)
    July 8, 1894. 3pp. Subject: Request for federal troops in Idaho. Begins at 0580.
  - Subfile 62. Pennsylvania, 1894; 13 (Reel 3)
    June 30-July 7, 1894. 10pp. Subject: Request for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0583.
  - Subfile 70. Tennessee, 1894-1895; 14 (Reel 3)
    July 5, 1894-May 2, 1895. 27pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; mob violence and intimidation; protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0593.
  - Subfile 77. Utah Territory, 1894-1895; 15 (Reel 3)
    July 3, 1894-Septembe 18, 1895. 60pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike; requests for reimbursement of railroads for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals; mob violence and intimidation; use of injunctions in labor disputes; use of federal troops to restore order. Begins at 0620.
  - Subfile 81. Washington, 1894-1895; 16 (Reel 3)
    July 6, 1894-May 25, 1895. 66pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins 0680.
  - Subfile 85. Wisconsin, 1894-1896; 17 (Reel 3)
    July 9, 1894-March 3, 1896. 63pp. Subjects: Indictment of Eugene V. Debs and other leaders of the American Railway Union for interfering with normal operations of railroads during strike; employment of special counsel in case; U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0746.
  - Subfile 87. Wyoming, 1894-1895; 18 (Reel 3)
    July 1, 1894-March 4, 1895. 29pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; requests for reimbursement of railroads for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals during Coxeyite or Industrial Army incidents; requests for federal troops; mob violence and intimidation; protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0809.
  - Subfile 90. President [Grover Cleveland], 1895; 19 (Reel 3)
    January 15-October 8, 1895. 11pp. Subjects: Trial of individual accused of wrecking a train in Michigan; request for payment of deputy in Colorado. Begins at 0838.
  - Subfile 91. From Members of Congress, 1894-1897; 20 (Reel 3)
    July 12, 1894-May 14, 1897. 60pp. Subjects: Requests and authorization for settlement of accounts of U.S. Marshals and deputies; mob violence and intimidation in Idaho mines; indictment and trial of strikers in California; requests for employment of special counsel. Begins at 0849.
- Casefile 16-1 End and 16-2 (Reel 4)
  - Subfile 92. Department of Justice, 1895-1896; 1 (Reel 4)
    Jul 12, 1895-September 26, 1896. 32pp. Subjects: Requests for reimbursement of railroads for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals; employment of private detectives as deputies. Begins 0000.
  - Subfile 93. Post Office, 1894; 2 (Reel 4)
    June 28-July 27, 1894. 38pp. Subjects: Protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike; Stoppage of mails in Arkansas, Tennessee, Ohio, Michigan, Montana, Minnesota, New Mexico, Colorado, Nevada, Iowa, Missouri, Illinois, Idaho, Kentucky, and California. Begins at 0032.
  - Subfile 95. Supreme Court, 1895; 3 (Reel 4)
    March 27-October18, 1895. 9pp. Subjects Acknowledgements of papers received in appeals of cases against Eugene V. Debs and other leaders of the American Railway Union. Begins at 0070.
  - Subfile 95. Treasury, 1894-1897; 4 (Reel 4)
    July 5, 1894-July 7, 1897. 52pp. Subjects: U.S. Marshal explanations of expenses incurred and deployment of deputies guarding railroad property; requests for reimbursement of railroads for funds advanced to U.S. Marshals; employment of special counsel in case against Eugene V. Debs and other leaders of the American Railway Union; use of federal troops to restore order in Arizona Territory and California. Begins at 0079.
  - Subfile 96. War Department, 1894-1897; 5 (Reel 4)
    July 6, 1894-July 31, 1897. 60pp. Subjects: Use of federal troops to restore order in Idaho, Nevada, California, Indian Territory, Oklahoma Territory, Utah, Montana, Washington, and Illinois; mob violence and intimidation; U.S. Marshal deployment of deputies in Arkansas; protection of U.S. mails and interstate commerce as justification for federal involvement in strike. Begins at 0131.
  - Section 1, 1902; 6 (Reel 4)
    May 16-September 29, 1902. 155pp. Subjects: Letters and petitions to President Theodore Roosevelt urging federal arbitration or federal seizure of coal mines; public sympathy and antipathy for strikers; cover letters to report to the president on the anthracite coal strike by the Commissioner of Labor; protests against trusts and combines among American businesses; local union protests against the use of injunctions in labor disputes involving William B. Wilson and Mother Jones of UMWA; interference with interstate commerce as possible justification for federal intervention in strike. Begins at 0191.
  - Section 2, 1902; 7 (Reel 4)
    October 1-December 14, 1902. 301pp. Subjects: Letters and petitions to President Theodore Roosevelt urging federal arbitration or federal seizure of coal mines; protests against trusts and combines among American businesses; proposed legislation for the regulation of corporations and unions; proposed antitrust proceedings against UMWA and coal operators. Begins at 0346.
  - Section 3, 1903; 8 (Reel 4)
    May 26-June 2, 1903. 191pp. Subject: Interstate Commerce Commission proceedings of William Randolph Hearst against railroads and coal companies concerning price-fixing and transportation contracts in the coal markets. Begins at 0647.
  - Section 4, 1903; 9 (Reel 4)
    January 13-December 29, 1903. 78pp. Subjects: Correspondence concerning Interstate Commerce Commission proceedings of William Randolph Hearst against railroads and coal companies concerning price-fixing and transportation contracts in the coal markets; U.S. Supreme Court; letters and petitions to President Theodore Roosevelt urging federal action against coal operators.
  - Section 5, 1904-1908; 10 (Reel 4)
    February 29, 1904-December 8. 1908 and Undated. 45pp. Subjects: Correspondence concerning Interstate Commerce Commission proceedings of William Randolph Hearst against railroads and coal companies concerning price-fixing and transportation contracts in the coal markets; U.S. Supreme Court; U.S. Circuit Court decision in case; legislative history of law enabling use of federal troops. Begins at 0916.
- Casefile 16-4 through 16-32 (Reel 5)
  - [Western Federation of Miners Strike in Alaska Territory] Casefile 16-4, 1908; 1 (Reel 5)
    February 3-June 9, 1908. 127pp. Subjects: Proposed use of federal troops; mob violence and intimidation; U.S. Marshal explanation of expenses and deployment of deputies an appointment of deputies guarding mines; cooperation of Mine Owners and Operations Association in appointment of deputies; employment of Russian workers as strikebreakers. Begins at 0000.
  - [San Francisco Street Car Strike and U.S. Smelting Refining and Mining Company Strike] Casefile 16-7-0, 1907-1941; 2 (Reel 5)
    May 15-16, 1907 and July 2, 1941. 14pp. Subjects: Settlement of strike at U.S. Smelting Refining and Mining Company operations at Fairbanks, Alaska Territory, in 1941; proposals for deputizing bodyguards of the governor of California during San Francisco streetcar and telephone workers strike in 1907. Begins at 0128.
  - [New Orleans Longshore Strike] Casefile 18-8, 1907; 3 (Reel 5)
    October 5-12, 1907. 13pp. Subjects: Opinion of Secretary of Commerce and Labor Oscar s. Straus concerning the use of injunctions in labor disputes; request by U.S. Attorney for authorization to ask for injunction; general strike of all labor engaged in handling freight in the port of New Orleans. Begins at 0142.
  - [Seattle Longshore Strike] Casefile 16-9, 1908; 4 (Reel 5)
    Jul 28-August 5, 1908. 31pp. Subject: U.S. Marshal appointment of deputies. Begins at 0155.
  - [Georgia Railroad Strike] Casefile 16-10, 1900-1909; 5 (Reel 5)
    May 14, 1900 and May 20-August 6, 1909. 44pp. Subjects: Arbitration of dispute between the Georgia Railroad Company and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; union protests against employment of Negus as locomotive firemen; protection of U.S. mails as justification for federal involvement in strike; mob violence and intimidation; memorandum of duties of postal officials and employees in cases of strikes on railroads carrying the mails; instructions for U.S. Attorney in St. Louis, Missouri, during street ca strike of 1900 as guidelines for handling the situation in Georgia. Begins at 0186.
  - [Illinois Central Railroad and Yazoo and Mississippi Valley Railroad Strike of Brotherhood of Railway Clerks in Tennessee, Mississippi and Louisiana] Casefile 16-16, 1911-1912; 6 (Reel 5)